Guide to the Brander Matthews Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence, 1876-1926
  - White, Stanford (Box 20)
  - White, Stuart Edward (Box 20)
  - White, William Allen (Box 20)
  - Whitman, Walt (Box 20)
  - Whitridge, Lucy T. (Box 20)
  - Wilde, Percival (Box 20)
  - Willard, Edward Smith (Box 20)
  - Williams, James (Box 20)
  - Williams, Thomas H. (Box 20)
  - Wilson, Francis (Box 20)
  - Wilson, Woodrow (Box 20)
  - Wilstach, Frank Jenners (Box 20)
  - Wilstach, Paul (Box 20)
  - Winter, Jefferson (Box 20)
  - Winter, William (Box 20)
  - Wister, Owen (Box 20)
  - Woodberry, George E. (Box 20)
  - Worthington, John (Box 20)
  - Wright, Frederich Amaziah (Box 20)
  - Yamamoto, Kuzaburo (Box 20)
  - Zola, Emile (Box 20)
- Series II: Writings
  This series contains notes, typescripts, contracts, book reviews, articles and clippings. The material is arranged chronologically within 9 subseries: Fiction, Plays, Verse, Biographies, Essays and Critiques, Pamphlets, Books edited, Introductions, Articles and Lectures. 1871-1923, 3.5 linear feet
  - Subseries II.1: Bibliography
    - Bibliography (Box 20)
  - Subseries II.2: Fiction
    - Robert Bright, May 29, 1875, (1 scrapbook) (Box 233, Folder Scrapbook Vol. 1)
    - The Last Meeting, 1885 (Box 20)
    - A Secret of the Sea, 1886 (Box 20)
    - A Family Tree, 1889-1890 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - With My Friends, 1891 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Tom Spaulding, 1892 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Story of a Story, 1893 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Vignettes of Manhattan, 1894, 1921-1923 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Royal Marine, 1894 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - The Sin of the Father, 1894 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Tales of Fantasy and Fact, 1896 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - His Father's Son, 1896 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - Outlines in Local Color, 1897 (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - A Confident Tomorrow, 1899 (Box 21, Folder 10)
      [See also X812M43/P]
    - Action and the Word, 1900 (Box 21, Folder 11)
    - Vistas of New York, 1912 (Box 21, Folder 12)
    - These Many Years, 1917 (Box 21, Folder 13)
    - Copyrights assigned by Harper and Brothers, 1921 (Box 21, Folder 14)
    - Notes for picaresque novel about New York (Box 21, Folder 15)
  - Subseries II.3: Plays
    - On Probation, 1871 (Box 21, Folder 16)
      [See also X812M43/M, Plays in 4 vol.]
    - On Probation, 1889 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Margery's Lovers, 1884 (Box 22, Folder 2 & 3)
    - The Partnership, 1884 (Box 22, Folder 4)
      [Written with H. L. Bunner]
    - The Irish Brigade, 1886 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - A Gold Mine, 1887 (Box 22, Folder 6 & 7)
    - This Picture and That, 1887-1894 (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - The Decision of the Court, 1893 (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - Notes for Nat Goodwin portrayal, 19 May 1898 (Box 22, Folder 10)
    - Peter Stuyvesant, 1899 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - The Selfish Mr. Selbourne, c.1904 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - High Spirits, 1905 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - What Shall It Profit, 1907 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Undated/unpublished plays (Box 23, Folder 6-12)
  - Subseries II.4: Verse
    - Fugitives From Justice, other verses, 1912 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Subseries II.5: Biographies
    - Moliere: His Life and Works, 1910 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Shakspere as a Playwright, 1916 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Subseries II.6: Essays and Criticism
    - The Theatres of Paris, 1880 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - French Dramatists, 1881 (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Home Library [under the name Arthur Penn], 1883 (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Pen and Ink, 1888 (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - Americanisms and Briticisms, 1892 (Box 24, Folder 8)
    - Studies of the Stage, 1894 (Box 24, Folder 9)
    - Bookbinding Old and New, 1895 (Box 24, Folder 10)
    - Books and Playbooks, 1895 (Box 24, Folder 11)
    - Aspects of Fiction, 1896 (Box 24, Folder 12)
    - Introduction to American Literature, 1893-1918 (Box 24, Folder 13)
    - The Historical Novel; Parts of Speech, 1901, ( ) (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Development of the Drama, 1803 (Box 25, Folder 2)
      [See also X812M43/P5]
    - Recreations of an Anthologist, 1804 (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - Inquiries and Opinion, 1907 (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - The American of the Future, 1909 (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - A Study of the Drama, 1910 (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - A Study of Versification, 1911 (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - Gateways to Literature, 1912 & 1913 (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - Book About the Theater, 1916 (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - Principles of Playmaking, 1919 (Box 25, Folder 10)
    - Essays on English, 1921 (Box 25, Folder 11)
    - Playwrights on Playmaking, 1923 (Box 25, Folder 12)
    - Tocsin of Revolt, 1924 (Box 25, Folder 13)
    - Essays idea (Box 25, Folder 14)
  - Subseries II.7: Pamphlets
    - The Philosophy of the Short Story, 1901 (Box 25, Folder 15)
    - Notes on Speechmaking, 1901 (Box 25)
    - American Characters, 1906 (Box 25)
    - On Acting, 1914 (Box 25)
    - Venetian Glass (Box 25)
  - Subseries II.8: Books edited
    - Comedies for Amateur Acting, 1879 (Box 25, Folder 16)
      [See also X812M43/S62, An editorial correspondence: Brander Matthews to Munro]
    - Poems of American Patriotism, 1882 (Box 25, Folder 16)
    - Actors and Actresses (written with Laurence Hutton), 1886 (Box 25, Folder 16)
    - The Dramatic Essays of Charles Lamb, 1892 (Box 25, Folder 16)
    - American Familiar Verse, 1904 (Box 25, Folder 17)
    - The Short Story, 1908 (Box 25, Folder 18)
      [See also X812M43/S62. An editorial correspondence: Matthews to Munro]
    - Lope de Vega's The New Art of Writing Plays, 1914, ( ) (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Oxford Book of American Essays, 1914 (Box 26)
    - Dramatic Museum, 2nd series, 1915 (Box 26)
    - Dramatic Museum, 3rd series, 1916 (Box 26)
    - Chief European Dramatists, 1916 (Box 26)
    - Chief British Dramatists, 1924 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Poems About Players, 1915 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Subseries II.9: Introductions
    - Whitcomb, S. L. Chronological Outlines of American Literature, 1894 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Subseries II.10: Articles and Lectures
    - "Memories of Edwin Booth" -- "Cleopatra's Nose" -- "Critics and Creators" -- "Doctor Johnson as a Conversationalist" -- "The Dunlap Society", 1914 (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - "Grolier Club" -- "Howlers" (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - "Negro Minstrelsy, The Decline and Fall of" -- "New York by a New Yorker, Notes on" -- "President's English" -- "Punch and Judy" (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - "Sayings of a Philosopher" -- "Show Business" -- "Sky-Pilots" -- "Spelling" -- "The Swift Passing of the Humorists" -- "Twain, Memories of Mark" (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - "Unanswerable Questions" -- "Variety Show" -- "What is Pure English?" -- "Wine, Woman, and Money", 1915 (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - Magazine articles, 1881-1903 (Box 26, Folder 10)
    - Magazine articles, 1904-1926 (Box 27, Folder 1 & 2)
    - Lectures (Box 27, Folder 3-6)
- Series III: Notes, 1872-1924
  This series is divided into three subseries: Author files, Subject files and Drama. It contains notes, clippings and articles on subjects in which Matthews had an interest. The notes are often written on small scraps of paper. Matthews would jot down any idea as soon as it occurred to him and throw it into a drawer "where I keep all such stray thoughts." Eventually he would organize these scraps and file them in envelopes. He considered each envelope "a story, or an essay in process of hatching." The files are arranged alphabetically within subseries. 6 linear feet
  - Subseries III.1: Author Files
    - Aeschylus, [n.d.] (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - T. B. Aldrich -- William Archer -- Aristophanes -- Emile Augier -- Jane Austen, [n.d.] (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Balzac -- Beaumarchais -- Bjornson -- Boccaccio (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - Bourget -- Charlotte Bronte -- Browning -- William Cullen Bryant (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - Calderon -- Cellini -- Cervantes -- James Fennimore Cooper -- Corneille -- George W. Curtis (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - Samuel Clemens (Mark Twain) (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - Gabriele D'Annunzio -- Daudet -- Georges Daudin -- Defoe (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - Dickens -- Dryden -- Dumas pere -- Dumas fils, [n.d.] (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - Echegaray -- Maria Edgeworth -- George Eliot (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - Ralph Waldo Emerson (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - Euripides (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - Octave Feuillet -- Fielding -- Stephen Foster -- Anatole France -- Benjamin Franklin (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - Goethe -- Goldsmith (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - Fitz-Greene Halleck and Joseph Rodman Drake -- Thomas Hardy -- Bret Harte -- Gerhart Hauptmann -- Hawthorne (Box 29, Folder 7)
    - Oliver Wendell Holmes (Box 29)
    - William Dean Howells, [n.d.] (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Victor Hugo (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - Ibsen (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - Washington Irving (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - Henry James -- Kotzebue -- Madame de Lafayette -- Le Sage -- Lessing -- Abraham Lincoln -- Lope de Vega (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - Rudyard Kipling (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - Longfellow (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - James Russell Lowell (Box 30, Folder 8)
    - James Russell Lowell, [n.d.] (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - Maeterlinck -- Marivaux -- Philip Massinger -- Maupassant -- Melville -- Meredith (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - Moliere (Box 31, Folder 3-5)
    - Francis Parkman, 1872-1923 (Box 32, Folder 1)
    - Stephen Phillips -- Plautus (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - Edgar Allan Poe (Box 32, Folder 3)
    - Rabelais -- Racine -- Richardson -- Reynard -- Charles Reade -- Edmond Rostand -- Saint Pierre -- Victorien Sardou (Box 32, Folder 4)
    - Walter Scott (Box 32, Folder 5)
    - Eugene Scribe -- Seneca -- George Bernard Shaw -- Shakespeare (Box 32, Folder 6)
    - Richard Brinsley Sheridan (Box 32, Folder 7 & 8)
    - Smollet -- Sophocles -- Herbert Spencer -- Sterne -- Robert Louis Stevenson (Box 33, Folder 1)
    - Harriet Beecher Stowe -- Herman Sudermann -- Swift -- Terence -- Thackeray (Box 33, Folder 2)
    - Thoreau -- Tolstoi -- Trollope -- Turgenev -- Voltaire -- Wagner -- Walpole (Box 33, Folder 3)
    - Daniel Webster -- Whitman -- Whittier; Zola (Box 33, Folder 4)
  - Subseries III.2: Subject Files
    Includes articles, clippings, exams and notes
    - Advertising and Posers, 1901-1920 (Box 33, Folder 5-8)
    - American Literature (Box 33, Folder 6 & 7)
    - American/British Relations -- Americans on Guard -- Anecdotes (Box 33, Folder 8)
    - Books -- Characterization -- Colonial period -- Comparative literature -- Criticism -- De Senectute, 1879-1924 (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - Dialog writing (Box 34, Folder 2)
    - Essays -- Figures of Speech -- Gesta Romanorum -- Historians -- Idealism -- Inventions -- Journalism (Box 34, Folder 3)
    - Lecturing -- Literary Evolution -- Longman's Publishing House -- Magic -- Man elevator -- Marie Antoinette -- Masterpieces (Box 34, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 34, Folder 5)
    - Morality in Fiction and Drama -- Names for characters -- Negro minstrel song -- Niagara Falls -- Non-Americans -- Novel (Box 34, Folder 6)
    - Orators -- Plagiarism -- Poems -- Puppets, 1881-1922 (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - Quotations (Box 35, Folder 2 & 3)
    - Revolutionary Period; Romances (Box 35, Folder 4)
    - Short Story (Box 35, Folder 5)
    - Spelling -- Style -- Titles -- Transcendentalism -- War (Box 35, Folder 6)
    - Writing (Box 35, Folder 7)
  - Subseries III.3: Drama files
    - Drama, 1902-1915 (Box 35, Folder 8)
    - American Drama, 1881-1923 (Box 36, Folder 1)
    - Acting -- Actor's memories -- Acts -- Audience (Box 36, Folder 2)
    - Conventions (Box 36, Folder 3)
    - Criticism, Development of (Box 36, Folder 4)
    - Failures (Box 36, Folder 5)
    - Fiction; Folk theater; Greek Comedy (Box 36, Folder 6)
    - Greek Drama (Box 36, Folder 7)
    - Indexes [Very brittle, request assistance] (Box 36, Folder 8 & 9)
    - Italy (Box 36, Folder 10)
    - Medieval Theater (Box 36, Folder 11)
    - Morality plays, 1885-1909 (Box 37, Folder 1)
    - Nineteenth Century Drama (Box 37, Folder 2)
    - One-act play -- Political play -- Pantomime -- Repertory theater (Box 37, Folder 3)
    - Renewal of Drama (Box 37, Folder 4)
    - Roman Drama (Box 37, Folder 5)
    - Spanish Drama (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - Scene painting (Box 37, Folder 7)
    - Stage design -- Stage life -- Stage management -- Stroller and farces -- Survivals (Box 37, Folder 8)
    - Words and phrases of the theater (Box 37, Folder 9)
    - Scrapbook on playwrights, 1903-1910, (1 volume) (Box 233)
- Series IV: Works by Others, 1879-1923
  This series contains articles, manuscripts, poetry, essays, and autographs by other authors. 0.5 linear feet
  - John Kendrick Bang -- Joseph M. Beatty -- Edward Hamilton Bell -- Robert Bridges -- Henry Cuyler Bunner, 1883-1923 (Box 38, Folder 2)
  - Andrew Carnegie -- Samuel Clemons (Mark Twain) -- Thomas Stephens Collier -- Austin Dobson -- John Erskine (Box 38, Folder 3)
  - Emile Faguet -- Joseph Smith Fletcher -- Richard Watson Gilder -- Arthur Goodrich -- Ferris Greenslett -- James Ketelas Hackett -- Thomas Wentworth Higginson -- William Dean Howells -- Philip Curtis Humphrey -- Thomas Hutchinson (Box 38, Folder 4)
  - George Henry Jessop -- Henry Arthur Jones -- Andrew Lang (Box 38, Folder 5)
  - George Parsons Lathrop; George Henry Lewes (Box 38, Folder 6)
  - Don Marquis (Box 38)
  - Dobson, Austin At the Sign of the Lyre, New York: Henry Holt, 1885, (1 Volume [Ms.]) (Box 234)
  - M. L. Mayer -- Lillian Nordica -- Thomas Buchanan Read -- Robert Francis St. Clair Rosslyn -- John William Rogers -- Frank Dempster Sherman -- Monroe Smith -- Nichol Smith -- Ashley Horace Thorndike, 1879-1912 (Box 39, Folder 1)
- Series V: Personal files, 1827-1962
  This series contains photographs, menus, ticket stubs, club rosters, scrapbooks, and other Matthews memorabilia. It includes items Matthews used to refresh his memory when writing his autobiography These Many Years. There are also research notes from a 1961-1962 study by Herbert Kleinfeld. 2 linear feet.
  - Memorabilia used in These Many Years, 1827-1967 (Box 39, Folder 2)
    [See also X812M43/P53, Diaries, 1871-1994. Diary portions have been removed from 1871-1881; and 812M43/S, Journal begun December 21, 1928]
  - Bibliography -- Dedication of bust -- Eulogy in 1929 by George Clinton Odell (Box 39, Folder 3)
  - Photographs and drawings of Brander Matthews (Box 39, Folder 4)
  - Bookplate (Box 39, Folder 5)
    [ See also Box 41: woodblock of bookplate]
  - Prints and pictures (Box 39, Folder 6)
  - Ada Smith Matthews [stage name Ada Harland], photographs and playbill (Box 39, Folder 7)
  - Theater tickets, 1905-1910 (Box 39, Folder 8)
  - Clubs: rosters and membership form from the Atheneum Club and the Round Table Dining Club -- Dunlap Society membership letters (Box 39, Folder 9 & 10)
  - American Academy of Arts and Letters, 1910-1916 (Box 40, Folder 1)
    [See also Scrapbooks X812M43/BS and X812M43/BC. Both contain menus, letters, invitations, and autographs dating from 1884-1907]
  - Menus and greeting cards, 1885-1907 (Box 40, Folder 2)
  - Herbert Kleinfeld research notes, 1961-1962 (Box 40, Folder 3-5)
  - Mementos, [n.d.], (1 Loving cup, 1 woodblock of bookplate) (Box 41)
- Series VI: Scrapbooks
  - # 1: Robert Bright, May 29, 1875, (1 volume) (Box 233)
  - # 2: Theatrical Notes, (1 volume) (Box 233)
  - # 3: Scrapbook of newspaper clippings re. Brander Matthews, 1869-1926, (1 volume) (Box 233)
  - # 4: Clippings scrapbook, obituaries and reminiscences, 1929, (1 volume) (Box 234)
  - # 5: Theater Scrapbook, 1923-1925 (Box 234)